Finding Aid for News and Information Services (University of Michigan) Audiovisual Materials
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
- Audio Podcasts, 2006-2010
  - 2007
    - Obese children twice as likely to have diabetes 4/19/2007, .mp3 file; "Among school-aged children, obese children have a greater than twofold chance of having diabetes, compared with children of normal weight," Dr. Joyce Lee says. "The large number of children with diabetes in the U.S., and the potential for increasing numbers of children developing diabetes with the obesity epidemic, has serious implications for how these children will receive appropriate health care now and as they grow into adulthood."
    - A seasonal journey 4/23/2007, .mp3 file; Joanne Nesbitt chronicles her walk through one of U-M's most popular cultural attractions.
    - Substance abuse among Chilean Teens 5/14/2007, .mp3 file; This interdisciplinary effort will result in a 15-year perspective study that will not only lend insight into Latin America, but also should be applicable to further the understanding of substance use among all youths in the United States.
    - Improving the environment, creating economic opportunity 5/25/2007, .mp3 file; Policy blueprint, Michigan at a Climate Crossroads Strategies for Guiding the State in a Carbon-Constrained World, presented to Michigan legislators on May 23 presents compelling case that time is at hand to reform state regulations.
    - Immigration and Higher Education 6/4/2007, .mp3 file; John Burkhardt, is a U-M professor of higher education and director of the National Forum on Higher Education for the Public Good. He also serves as a special assistant to the provost for University engagement and organized ``Challenges and Opportunities: Conversations about immigration and higher education. He talks about where the nation is on this major issue being debated in Congress.
    - Star Light Star Bright 6/8/2007, .mp3 file; We talk to U-M astronomer John Monnier and graduate student Ming Zhao. They led an international team that combined light from four widely separated telescopes to produce the first picture showing surface details on a sun-like star beyond our solar system. It was a rapidly rotating, hot star called Altair.
    - Michigan Economy 6/25/2007, .mp3 file; Michigan will be a poorer state over the next decade, but its universities and resources like the Great Lakes can help reverse its declining economy.
    - Diabetes: Healthy knees and joints 7/2/2007, .mp3 file; People with diabetes who keep their blood sugar in check today will probably have a far lower chance of developing foot pain or other nerve damage tomorrow.
    - Considering History 7/27/2007, .mp3 file; Knowing the past sheds light on future possibilities.
    - Monitoring the Future 1: How it Began 8/3/2007, .mp3 file; Every year since 1975, University of Michigan researcher Lloyd Johnston's team has conducted the Monitoring the Future study of 50,000 young Americans. In this first part of a multi-part interview, Johnston describes how the survey that has interviewed more than 1 million people all began.
    - Auto talks 8/7/2007, .mp3 file; Current UAW contract talks with U.S. automakers may be the most important in decades.
    - Knee injuries fairly common 8/12/2007, .mp3 file; discussion with professor about ACL injuries and research into these.
    - The cars of the future 8/24/2007, .mp3 file; Engineering professor Zoran Filipi believes plug-in hybrid electric vehicles will be common on the highways of tomorrow. He explains how they work and why they could help reduce greenhouse gases.
    - Future forests 8/31/2007, .mp3 file; Birches will likely drive out aspens in northern forests as carbon dioxide levels continue to mount in coming decades.
    - Round gobies rising 9/7/2007, .mp3 file; Jude and Hensler discovered that newly hatched round gobies leave their lake bottom homes and swim to the surface at night, a nocturnal migration that increases the chances that large numbers of hatchlings will get sucked into the ballast tanks of Great Lakes freighters.
    - Frenk speaks at U-M 9/14/2007, .mp3 file; Julio Frenk, former minister of health of Mexico, and current counsel to the Bill and Melinda Gates Foundation talks about disaster preparedness at School of Public Health symposium on Sept. 11, 2007.
    - Renowned pianist visits U-M students on October 4, 2007 9/21/2007, .mp3 file; U-M Department of Music offers up close interaction with preeminent pianist.
    - Bo's Lasting Lessons 9/28/2007, .mp3 file; In the last years of his life, Bo Schembechler passed his leadership secrets to writer John U. Bacon. The result is a book, "Bo's Lasting Lessons: The Legendary Coach Teaches the Timeless Fundamentals of Leadership" that offers leaders both penetrating insight ("You can't lead people unless you like people") and practical advice ("Recruit for character"). Bacon discusses Bo's leadership style, and describes what it was like to work for the notoriously demanding coach.
    - The high costs of financial services for the poor 10/4/2007, .mp3 file; Low-income households in the United States often lack access to bank accounts and face high costs for conducting basic financial transactions through check cashiers and other alternative financial service providers. Law professor Michael Barr says these families find it more difficult to save and plan financially for the future.
    - Provocative exhibit in cyberspace 10/27/2007, .mp3 file; UM curators transform eBay into art gallery.
    - Schmoozing is good for the brain 10/29/2007, .mp3 file; Shooting the breeze for just 10 minutes boosts mental performance.
    - Identifying with fictional characters 11/5/2007, .mp3 file; Men looked more favorably toward smoking when they saw movie character John McCane (Die Hard) smoke.
    - What is MRSA? 11/12/2007, .mp3 file; Listen to Prof. Aiello explain how we protect ourselves against MRSA, and what the emergence of this in schools really means.
    - Dwindling drinking water 11/16/2007, .mp3 file; To cope with dwindling freshwater supplies, U-M professor Walter Weber discusses treating wastewater for drinking. He talks about his ideas for better water management and how we could extract energy from toilet water.
    - Seven years of bad luck 11/16/2007, .mp3 file; Michigan's economy has seen seven years of great plenty, followed by seven years of economic famine---but, unfortunately, it's not over yet, say University of Michigan economists.
    - Sleep: Getting enough? 11/29/2007, .mp3 file; U-M Psychology Chair Terri Lee is an expert on sleep and the circadian rhythms we all live by. Changing your natural rhythms -- particularly during adolescence -- can cause major problems, she warns.
    - Do you know what your children are watching? 12/7/2007, .mp3 file; "Watching media violence significantly increases the risk that a viewer or video game player will behave aggressively in both the short and long term, according to a University of Michigan study published today in a special issue of the Journal of Adolescent Health. The study, by L. Rowell Huesmann, reviews more than half a century of research on the impact of exposure to violence in television, movies, video games and on the Internet."The research clearly shows that exposure to virtual violence increases the risk that both children and adults will behave aggressively," said Huesmann, the Amos N. Tversky Collegiate Professor of Communication Studies and Psychology, and a senior research scientist at the U-M Institute for Social Research (ISR)."
    - Find the right motivation 12/12/2007, .mp3 file; Women who exercise for a body shape motive, such as wanting to lose weight or to become toned, spend about 40 percent less time exercising than women who exercise for motives not related to achieving a certain body shape or weight.
    - Can't find the perfect gift? 12/15/2007, .mp3 file; Gershoff says that we overestimate how much.
  - 2008
    - Enhancing shower and bathtub safety for the aged 1/6/2008, .mp3 file; Healthcare professionals should help prevent bathing accidents, not just treat people after they have had a fall in the bathroom.
    - Popular opinion not always popular 1/14/2008, .mp3 file; We often form opinions and make decisions based on a lone, repetitive voice that we mistake for a chorus.
    - Relationships over time 1/21/2008, .mp3 file; Analysis of data over 13 years with more than 800 adults shows that we're likely to see our spouses as more irritating and demanding as we age, while we are likely to see our relationships with children and friends more positively.
    - Fights good for health 1/21/2008, .mp3 file; This research is about how couple who resolve conflict live longer than those who do not.
    - I'm 25 and I still live with my parents 1/23/2008, .mp3 file; It takes young people longer to complete their schooling, settle into steady employment, and delay marriage and childbearing, according to new findings. Thus, it's become socially acceptable living with parents as an adult.
    - Success elevates profile of U-M screenwriters 2/9/2008, .mp3 file; Impressive list of U-M alumni making impact in Hollywood.
    - Subprime mortgage crisis 2/18/2008, .mp3 file; Robert Van Order of the Ross School of Business says America's faltering economy and overextended borrowers aren't the only causes of the subprime crisis -- lenders and investors are also to blame.
    - Good deeds and living longer 2/25/2008, .mp3 file; Helping others is good for the helper.
    - Students resolve conflict and bias through small group interactions 2/29/2008, .mp3 file; If students understand what causes conflicts and assumptions about others different from them, they are able to adapt later in life, according to a new University of Michigan study.
    - Kids who feel safe act more safely 3/4/2008, .mp3 file; Urban kids who feel safe delay gratification, behave less dangerously.
    - Is there media bias? 3/7/2008, .mp3 file; Hillary Clinton says the media coverage is pro-Barack Obama. This has forced some news organizations to take another look at their presidential election coverage, as well as take a closer look at Obama and his background. Bucy discusses the media coverage.
    - Power of caricature 3/18/2008, .mp3 file; In Goldstein's view, the power of an irreverent image, cartoon or illustration can appeal to the most people---and leave an indelible impression.
    - Financial bailouts and the Fed 3/31/2008, .mp3 file; University of Michigan finance professor explains what and why the Federal Reserve intervened in the Bear Stearns banking crisis.
    - A very intense laser 4/7/2008, .mp3 file; Victor Yanovsky, research scientist at U-M, discusses the laser beam that sets a world record for intensity.
    - Business and pleasure don't mix 4/11/2008, .mp3 file; Americans may not socialize with colleagues as much as workers in other countries do, but they enjoy it when they do.
    - Online Q and A forums hit the mainstream 4/18/2008, .mp3 file; Online question and answer forums are as old as the Internet, but they're reaching the mainstream and making the web more human, say two researchers who have just completed a large-scale study of Yahoo Answers.
    - Innocence sought for wrongly convicted 4/24/2008, .mp3 file; The University of Michigan Law School will open a new clinic in January that will assist prisoners convicted in cases where biological evidence like DNA doesn't exist. This Innocence Clinic is unique because other "Innocence Clinics" mainly handle cases involving DNA evidence.
    - The 70 Percent Solution for Reduction of Greenhouse Gases 4/28/2008, .mp3 file; MMPEI is working with other organizations on campus to develop a tool to help scientists and engineers project whether new cleaner technologies will take hold.
    - Pedometers prompting exercise 5/5/2008, .mp3 file; Researchers from the University of Michigan Health System and the Veterans Administration Ann Arbor Healthcare System say sedentary and overweight people with type two diabetes who participated in a walking study were more motivated to walk if they wore pedometers and consulted a Web site that tracked physicals activity.
    - It's not over until... (5/19/2008, .mp3 file; The last few primaries for the presidential candidates concludes soon, but many questions remain in the Democratic Party's two-person race.
    - Climate change and business 5/30/2008, .mp3 file; Regardless of one's stance on climate change, it makes economic sense for businesses and consumers to take climate-related action.
    - Energizing the URC 6/9/2008, .mp3 file; University of Michigan President Mary Sue Coleman and her fellow University Research Corridor presidents from Michigan State University and Wayne State University joined forces at the Mackinac Policy Conference. During the conference at the island's famous Grand Hotel, we asked the president about her vision for the URC, an alliance of Michigan's three research universities.
    - Tornado chasing 6/16/2008, .mp3 file; Professor Perry Samson recently returned from a storm chasing trip with students. He talks about where, why and what it was like.
    - Picking a U.S. vice president 6/19/2008, .mp3 file; Voters still focus on the first name on the ticket, not the VP choice.
    - Remarried caregivers 6/30/2008, .mp3 file; ISR researcher Carey Wexler Sherman is looking for participants in a new study of older remarried caregivers.
    - Solar car ready for race 7/7/2008, .mp3 file; Two student members of the U-M solar car team discuss the upcoming North American Solar Challenge and compare it to the World Solar Challenge, which took place in October. Spencer Bailey, who was in the car when it crashed in 2007, discusses the crash.
    - Breaking racial barriers 7/10/2008, .mp3 file; Sports fans know the story of Jackie Robinson, whose debut in 1947 ended an era of Jim Crow in the major leagues. As the Brooklyn Dodgers' president, U-M Law School graduate Branch Rickey signed Robinson.
    - Surviving sexual abuse 7/11/2008, .mp3 file; Mothers relive traumatic experience of sexual abuse during their childbearing years.
    - U-M students in India 7/21/2008, .mp3 file; Fifteen students will find ways to build bridges between the intellectual pursuits of an academic life and the mystic forces that for millennia shaped everyday life in India.
    - Energy expert Steve Forrest 7/28/2008, .mp3 file; U-M Vice President for Research Steve Forrest, an expert on energy research, discusses the opportunities to developing alternative energy research.
    - Computers in the classroom 8/4/2008, .mp3 file; Elliot Soloway has developed educational software for cell phones that allows them to be used in the classroom as personal computers. He discusses technology in the classroom.
    - It's time to party 8/12/2008, .mp3 file; Conventions no longer accomplish what they used to, such as shaping key messages and policies. They have turned out to be extravagant parties still covered by the media. U-M professor Michael Traugott talks about what is accomplished at conventions today and the significant moments that can define the remaining months until the November elections.
    - Environmental toxicants 8/18/2008, .mp3 file; The environment is playing a much larger role in everyday diseases. What are environmental toxicants and why do we know they contribute to health problems? University of Michigan professor Howard Hu explains.
    - Dorm room anxiety 8/25/2008, .mp3 file; Anxious college freshmen can relax. No matter who will be sharing their dorm room, they have the power to make the relationship better, say U-M researchers.
    - Improving literacy 9/8/2008, .mp3 file; Elizabeth Moje has spent years following and studying adolescents in southwest Detroit, to discover why many low income students struggle with reading. She's found many answers on how they read and interact and how to better teach the teachers.
    - American ideal 9/11/2008, .mp3 file; Young women look to their favorite female TV characters as role models for behavior and appearance.
    - Emotional recovery 9/17/2008, .mp3 file; New research shows that the best way to move ahead emotionally is to analyze one's feelings from a psychologically distanced perspective.
    - Nightmare on Wall Street 9/19/2008, .mp3 file; The current turmoil in America's financial markets is the worst since the Great Depression and Wall Street's response has made things worse. Regulation will make things better
    - Global aging symposium 9/23/2008, .mp3 file; Global aging and why should we care?
    - Bailout: Unpopular, needed 10/6/2008, .mp3 file; Now that Congress has passed the $700 billion bailout law, the American economy should begin to recover, but regulations are needed to prevent it from happening again.
    - Political attack mode 10/8/2008, .mp3 file; As the presidential campaigns wind down to their final weeks before Nov. 4th's election day, the number of negative television and radio ads seems to be increasing. University of Michigan professor Arthur Lupia and doctoral student Yanna Krupnikov say voters typically do not like negative ads, especially as some are still deciding which candidate should replace Bush in the Oval Office.
    - Values and voting 10/16/2008, .mp3 file; Wayne Baker, a Ross School professor and sociologist at the Institute for Social Research, discusses public reaction to the financial bailout and hot topics in the election.
    - M-flu results positive 10/23/2008, .mp3 file; The results suggest that masks and handwashing can reduce the spread of symptoms by as much as 50 percent.
    - Poll position 10/30/2008, .mp3 file; In a sense, Nov. 4 is judgment day. Election officials know if their efforts to improve the voting process is successful. Pollsters will learn if their reports were accurate.
    - Obama: How will he govern? 11/6/2008, .mp3 file; Americans are eager for President-elect Barack Obama to assume his position in the White. But will his leadership and governing style entail? Can he meet expectations? What does his election mean for the business world?
    - Estrogen can harm heart 11/18/2008, .mp3 file; Describes how women should decide whether to take insulin, and what it means if she has existing heart risk factors
    - Black Friday: Deals and deaths 12/2/2008, .mp3 file; Retail marketing professor Aradhna Krishna suggests four policies to prevent store stampedes.
    - Cure for gum disease? 12/9/2008, .mp3 file; Researchers discover a way to use gene therapy to slow and reverse the progression of periodontal disease.
    - Hardwired to overspend? 12/9/2008, .mp3 file; Professor Daniel Kruger looks to evolution to explain why we overspend.
  - 2009
    - Do the right thing 1/11/2009, .mp3 file; Chamberlin talks about politicians and business executives acting unethically.
    - Detroit Auto Show 2009 1/19/2009, .mp3 file; UMTRI's Bruce Belzowski provides overview of what GM, Ford, Chrysler, Honda and Toyota are featuring at this year's Detroit auto show.
    - Joycelyn Elders visits U-M 1/22/2009, .mp3 file; Joycelyn Elders, 15th Surgeon General under then President Bill Clinton, discusses current pressing public health issues of today
    - Intelligence: How to get it 2/1/2009, .mp3 file; Social psychologist Richard Nisbett discusses the impact of environment, including schools and culture, on the development of intelligence.
    - A change in foreign policy 2/6/2009, .mp3 file; Morrow talks about changes in foreign policy under the Obama administration
    - U-M energy research on rise 2/13/2009, .mp3 file; Collaborative energy-research partnerships will enable the University of Michigan to prosper while helping to diversify and revive the state's economy, according to Vice President for Research Stephen Forrest.
    - The impact of violent media 3/1/2009, .mp3 file; New research shows that playing violent video games and watching violent moves make people less empathic and sensitive to the suffering of others.
    - Greener computer data centers 3/5/2009, .mp3 file; By 2011, the nation's computer data centers will consume more power than 8 million average U.S. households. A new strategy cuts down on their energy waste by putting servers to sleep when they're not in use.
    - Execs on the hot seat 3/6/2009, .mp3 file; The days of the cozy relationship between executives and boards are gone.
    - Financial health of Europe 3/16/2009, .mp3 file; The European Union and the United States must work together to solve the world's economic crisis.
    - No spanking allowed 3/21/2009, .mp3 file; A new University of Michigan analysis finds that physical punishment does not improve children's behavior in the long term.
    - A modern form of slavery 3/25/2009, .mp3 file; Human trafficking is the second largest criminal activity in the world, generating billions of dollars annually. The new law clinic opens fall 2009 to help victims regain their lives.
    - Fostering a change for kids 4/7/2009, .mp3 file; The new advocacy clinic will provide legal representation and social work services to low-income families to prevent unnecessary placement and prolonged stay of children in foster care.
    - High morale in low times 4/20/2009, .mp3 file; Massive layoffs, budget cuts, closures. The news is bad enough for workers and executives who lose their jobs. But for those still employed, keeping morale high can be challenging.
    - Organic molecules in space 4/27/2009, .mp3 file; Astronomy professor Ted Bergin will use the Herschel Space Observatory to search for the building blocks of life in the clouds of gas and dust around young stars. His research could give new insights into how life began on Earth.
    - Coping with depression 5/4/2009, .mp3 file; These days, many people feel stressed by the high unemployment rates, foreclosures and personal income. U-M professor Melvin McInnis talks about what's happening and offers tips to cope with depression.
    - What is the URC? 5/22/2009, .mp3 file; U-M President Mary Sue Coleman will join Michigan State University President Lou Anna Simon and Wayne State University President Jay Noren at Mackinac Island May 28 to release a new University Research Corridor report. Coleman answers the question ``What is the URC in this one minute podcast.
    - Adult kids and their parents 5/29/2009, .mp3 file; New research shows that it's common for adult children and their parents to annoy each other. The research identifies common sources of irritation, and how parents and adult kids cope.
    - Scarce men likelier to scram 6/8/2009, .mp3 file; When young men are scarce, they're more likely to play the field than to propose
    - Tips to stop flu spread 6/12/2009, .mp3 file; JoLynn Montgomery of the School of Public Health defines pandemic, and provides some simple steps people can take to protect themselves and other from flu symptoms.
    - Changing poverty 6/16/2009, .mp3 file; More than 37 million people are considered poor. U-M expert Sheldon Danziger says the Obama Administration could have policies in place to lower the poverty rate in the next few years.
    - Genetic testing debate 7/15/2009, .mp3 file; Researcher Scott Roberts discusses the debate over direct to consumer genetic testing.
    - The legacy of Apollo 11 7/16/2009, .mp3 file; Forty years after the first lunar landing, astronaut and associate dean in the College of Engineering Tony England discusses the significance of Apollo 11 and the future of U.S. space travel and science.
    - Sports injury prevention 7/23/2009, .mp3 file; Professor Scott McLean discusses how sports injury prevention training programs could differ in the future.